Hello all and welcome to our last section here for the dev ops tutorials.
So in the last section here we will implement the infrastructure as a code or Terraform.
So the objective here to automate the provisioning of Docker based WordPress, which means
I won't just to run the Terraform instead of typing all the commands to start and enable
the Docker and creation on the Docker.
I would use the Terraform as infrastructure as a code to automate that process.
So first let install it with install it, there is several methods, but we will install it using
the hashicorp, which is the official repository.
So let's, we have already the young configuration manager, so let's download it.
This is our last session in which we have enabled the GitHub runner, which is internal
on our system or virtual machine.
So let's now, let's now download or adding the repositories, we have added the repositories
of hashicorp and now we will install simply the Terraform.
Okay, I will pause the video because it will take some time for the install and download
an installation of Terraform and once it's finished, I will return back to you.
Okay, great, we have installed now the Terraform and no need for the validation for the
version as it is installed with the version 1.14, great.
So now let's proceed with our task first.
First we create Terraform configurations for the following task.
We want the Docker network container communication case, so we will automate the creation
of the Docker along with the networking connectivity between them.
We use the MySQL, not Maria database as a storage, okay, for the MySQL container and
we use a patch HP container with mounting or mounted volume for WordPress and we sure
that containers of course are on the same network and I will show you finally how to
validate or integrate the Terraform by using CI CD tools and finally after we initialize
and apply the Terraform configuration, I will show you how we can verify the WordPress
by connecting to the HTTP access local host and verify access to the database.
So the first step here, let's make a directory which we call Terraform or press, okay.
This will be in our home directory as usual that in our lab, so as we have done for
the GitLab for example, my in the home direction, I can see my GitLab directory and also
here we can find the Terraform and let's switch to, okay, CD tilde and we are now on
the Terraform WordPress.
So we create the Terraform has three things to be created, okay, this is the file structure
or the core structure of the Terraform, you need to create the main file variables and
output file, okay, so let's create all of these three files and I will explain to you
in details what, why we need these files, okay, they are created, let's verify, okay,
this is the main outputs and variables.
So here let's create the first file, the first file to create is the Terraform, okay,
so for example here, this is the first part, we will create the Terraform and the Docker
which will be down the Terraform which actually the Terraform will manage or automate everything,
so let's first edit the main.df file, okay, and this file is something like the main file
function, okay, the main functions are configured or are written here, okay, so we have
providers that require providers for the Terraform, we have Docker and this is the source
for the Docker and this is the version of Docker that we are using and the Terraform
when he wants to manage the Docker, he will use the provider Docker, okay, so this
is the provider Docker and this is Docker network, we have the resource called Docker network
and called WP underscore network in which we will connect the MySQL and my PHP Apache
containers to it and this is the name of our network, WP underscore network, this is the Docker
networks, okay, and here we go down, let's now create start with the database, okay, we will create
Docker volume first, okay, course not here, we need to create it here, okay, this is our volume,
MySQL data, okay, this is the name of it MySQL underscore data, this is the storage for MySQL,
okay, this is the name of it, okay, and let's create the container itself, resource called Docker
container because created the mounted volume, we need to create the container, container is named
MySQL, okay, and we'll define here the image that we want to use and we'd use here a different
name for example, word press, word press dash MySQL and this is our image MySQL, it is the same
one that we have used and also here we use the mixer restart as always to restart the container
when needed and we would set some environment variables and here is the thing, let me put
here first comments, okay, here if you can see we have we had explained already your image name
restart and the environment here is only pointing to some variables, so here the link between
the two files, we have the main file and the variable file will contain values for this, for
example, there is a field for the password, MySQL database, MySQL user and user password,
all of these environment variables are just initiated in the main file and we'll be defined
later in the variable.tf file, so we have created initials or initialized variables and here's a
volume, we'll create a volume, okay, create a volume name, docker volume, lock MySQL.name, okay,
and we need to specify the container path for the database to work correctly, you need to set the
path for to be valid MySQL, so the volume, okay, docker volume.mySQL.name for our MySQL data, okay,
we'll be stored in this path exactly, and network advance of course do not forget this before we
close this SQL container, don't forget to type the network advance because network advance as you
if you can recall this is the docker network, we will be a member of docker network,
WP network botany, so this is our docker network that we have created earlier here,
docker or WP underscore network, it is WP here underscore network, okay, and we close the brackets
because we want to close the brackets that we have created for MySQL, this one, this is the closure
for this brackets, okay, and we'll repeat the same step, we'll still on the main file but we need to
create, we'll use of course the same rich feature the PHP Apache image, we'll repeat the same steps
for Apache and PHP and WordPress container, so this you need to make sure that this still exists
still exists on our system, so we are cool, and now we need to create, okay, this time we need to
create a PHP Apache container, so here we have created the container, we named it WP dash Apache,
and this is image that it is using, and it is, it starts at always, and this is the internal
and external port set to 8080, and we can set to any port set to be wish of course,
and the volume will be set to home of home mmm, mmm, more www of course, and the container path
will be treated as an application, so we need to define volume as we have did with the SQL,
and here, after that we need to define the variable for the web document root, we set to app,
for this we need to be identified for all the files that we have for our website, for example,
and the PHP memory limit we set to not make any exhaustive use of memory, we set it to 500 and 12
megabytes, this is just to boost hardware performance, nothing more, okay, and the last step here that
we need of course set the network advance to the member of the same network adapter of SQL,
okay, the same comment, and here don't forget to make this because it depends on the container
of MySQL, because there will be a backend connectivity between Apache web server and MySQL,
so it should depend on it, and we should define that line as well, okay, so after we set this,
these brackets of course you will see that this is closed by this, of course you need to have
special type of a different facility, t2 is opening and closure of packet, but if you can trace it,
it is very easy, you can see that it is the closure of the container of PHP this time,
or Apache web server this time, okay, so we need to save it, control O,
and if we open it again, you can see that it is successfully edited or filled with the data that we want,
okay, so let's move now to the second part, which is the variables, we'll edit now the variable,
okay, so here we need to set as I've told you MySQL, password, MySQL database, MySQL user,
okay, so we need,